We ask a lot of questions
about our diet.
What’s the right way to
treat a chronic illness?
Fight off a virus,
lose weight?
The problem is, we get
a lot of different answers.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
The new class
of weight-loss drugs,
GLP-1 agonists like Ozempic,
have received enormous,
almost unprecedented, attention
in the mainstream media.
They’ve been called "the medical
sensation of the decade."
The business press
was practically giddy,
declaring the end
of the obesity epidemic.
The enthusiasm is shared
in the medical literature,
with headlines suggesting
they are game-changing
revolutions
in the treatment of obesity:
therapeutic-wizard miracle drugs
that are hugely effective
in the treatment of obesity.
But history is littered with
failed weight-loss wonder drugs.
Every other year or so,
an anti-obesity medication
that had been approved
to be safe and effective
has had to be withdrawn
from the market
after serious side effects
emerged.
To date, most weight-loss drugs,
despite their initial approval,
have since been
pulled from the market
for unforeseen side effects
that have turned them
into a public threat.
From "rainbow diet pills"
packed with amphetamines
that were marketed to women,
to the rise and fall of fen-phen
(which triggered catastrophic
heart and lung conditions),
history is beset
by failures to find
safe, successful
weight-loss drugs.
Aminorex was a widely prescribed
appetite suppressant
before it was pulled
for causing lung damage.
Eighteen million Americans
were on fen-phen
before it was pulled for causing
severe damage to heart valves.
Meridia was pulled
for heart attacks and strokes,
and Acomplia for psychiatric
side effects, including suicide.
Belviq was withdrawn in 2020
after it was recognized that
it may have been causing cancer
for the eight years
it had been on the market.
The U.S. Food and Drug
Administration
initially rejected it
after it appeared to cause
several types of tumors in rats,
but when a one-year human trial
showed no apparent cancer,
it was approved
and went on to become
one of the most frequently
prescribed weight-loss drugs.
But when people were actually
on it for a few years,
notably high rates of colorectal
cancer, pancreatic cancer,
and lung cancer popped up;
so, oopsey,
it was pulled from the market.
The news was met
with surprise and confusion
among obesity medicine
specialists,
who had been
prescribing the drug
to help patients
achieve and sustain
the health benefits
of weight loss.
It was particularly jarring,
because the drug was generally
regarded as being so safe,
until it wasn’t.
Or take Benfluorex,
like Ozempic,
another diabetes drug repurposed
as an appetite suppressant.
It caused hundreds of deaths,
but didn’t get pulled
for 33 years.
The drug company knew about
the risks, but covered them up.
Judges concluded
that the drug company’s priority
was systematically given to
"preserving
its own economic interests
over the safety
of the drug’s consumers."
So, historically,
anti-obesity drugs have been
kind of like cigarettes.
Like smoking,
popping these pills
can cause you to lose weight,
but at what cost?
The goal of weight loss is not
to fit into a skinnier casket.
But they don’t even work
very well.
The current crop of
approved meds includes Qsymia,
a combination of phentermine,
the phen in fen-phen,
and topiramate, a drug
that can cause seizures
if you abruptly stop taking it.
This drug combination
was explicitly rejected
multiple times
for safety reasons in Europe
but remains for sale
in the United States.
Contrave is another option,
if you choose to ignore
its own black-box warning
about a potential increase
in suicidal thoughts.
Alli, also sold as Xenical,
is the final choice.
That’s the drug
that blocks fat absorption
and causes side effects such
as "flatus with discharge."
The drug evidently "forces
the patient to use diapers
and to know the location
of all the bathrooms
in the neighborhood
in an attempt
to limit the consequences
of urgent leakage
of oily fecal matter."
All for a grand total
of just 3 percent weight loss.
All that mess to go from, like,
300 pounds (135 kg)
down to 291 pounds (130 kg).
As you can see,
older weight-loss medications
only achieved about
5 percent weight loss,
whereas the newfangled
GLP-1 agonists like Ozempic
can cause an average of...
6 percent weight loss!
Now, this is because they were
averaging the effects
of some of the older GLP-1
agonists like Saxenda or Byetta.
Semaglutide,
sold as Ozempic for diabetes
and Wegovy for weight loss,
causes about twice that.
And now, there’s tirzepatide,
sold as Mounjaro or Zepbound,
which gets you closer to what
you see with bariatric surgery.
So, while the older
obesity medications achieve
weight losses in
the 5 to 10 percent range,
the new generation of agents
are more in
the 15 to 20 percent range,
about triple what we saw
in many of the older drugs.
So, for about half a century,
there’s been healthy skepticism
about new-kid-on-the-block
obesity drugs
promising profound weight loss,
only to see one after another
fail and flop,
but today, this historical
narrative could be in flux.
Even over just
the last decade or so,
obesity rates have
spiraled out of control.
Are GLP-1 receptor activators
the long-sought-after panacea
for obesity?
Well, first of all,
what is GLP-1?
The gastrointestinal tract
is known
as the largest hormone-secreting
gland in the human body,
releasing more than 20
peptide hormones.
About 1 out of every 100 cells
lining our entire digestive
tract acts as a nutrient sensor
and can secrete hormones
accordingly,
including GLP-1,
glucagon-like peptide-1.
The primary stimuli
for GLP-1 secretion
are meals rich in fats
and carbohydrates,
and the main action of GLP-1 is
to signal nutritional abundance
to the brain,
reducing our appetite
so we don’t eat
too many doughnuts.
GLP-1 also slows things down,
allowing us more time to digest,
and the slowing of the rate
at which food leaves our stomach
helps with blood sugar control
after a meal.
So, GLP-1 hormone-mimicking
drugs were actually
first developed to treat
type 2 diabetes.
The reason you can’t just
give people GLP-1 directly
is because it’s broken down
so quickly,
it hardly even makes it
one time around the circulation,
thanks to inactivation
by an enzyme in our body.
But then,
a compound was discovered
that activates GLP-1 activity
but was resistant
to enzyme breakdown.
And it was found in a lizard.
It’s a constituent
of Gila Monster venom.
And the first drug was born.
Using that as a template,
the first GLP-1 agonist
was created
and approved
for the treatment of diabetes
about 20 years ago.
Instead of half lasting
2.5 minutes in the body,
it lasted about 2.5 hours,
but still had to be injected
twice a day.
Then came liraglutide,
which lasts all day,
but even once-a-day injections
can be a pain.
Enter semaglutide,
branded as Ozempic,
which could be injected
just once a week.
It was approved to treat
diabetes in 2017.
Within a few years, a daily oral
version had been developed,
again for diabetes,
but researchers running
those clinical trials
noticed a surprising
side effect:
people’s appetites diminished.
Indeed, if you drip the hormone
GLP-1 into people’s veins,
it reduces their appetite,
leading
to decreased food intake.
And not just a little.
We’re talking about
a decrease in caloric intake
by as much as 25 to 50 percent.
The GLP-1 hormone not only
slows stomach emptying--
so you feel fuller longer
after eating--
but also works
as an appetite suppressant
by triggering
parts of the brain
responsible
for hunger and cravings.
GLP-1-secreting cells don’t
only line our intestines;
they’re also in our brains.
So, GLP-1 agonist drugs,
meaning GLP-1-mimicking drugs,
work kind of like
the way birth control pills do.
Birth control pills mimic
placental hormones,
thereby tricking our body
into thinking we’re pregnant
all the time.
Ozempic-type drugs mimic GLP-1,
thereby tricking our body
into thinking
we’re eating all the time;
so, it dials down
our hunger drive.
In 2021, semaglutide,
originally approved as Ozempic
to treat diabetes,
was rebranded at a higher dose
as Wegovy to treat obesity,
and the weight-loss industry
changed overnight,
shifting away
from meal replacements
and portion-control plans
to the new world
of private equity-funded
telemedicine entities
set up to offer these
injectable weight-loss drugs.
Even Weight Watchers has openly
embraced these kinds of drugs
as the future of weight loss.
They were even approved
for kids as young as age 12--
tweens, not even teens.
Is that a good idea?
What are the pros and cons
of these new
weight-loss medications?
Older weight-loss
medications achieve
approximately 5 percent
reduction in body weight
over placebo,
whereas these new GLP-1
agonists, like Ozempic,
produce about triple the effect,
about 15 percent.
But what does that mean in terms
of numbers on the scale?
In an analysis of more than
100 clinical trials
of earlier anti-obesity
medications,
in studies lasting
up to 76 weeks,
drug-induced weight loss
never exceeded
more than 9 pounds (4 kg).
If you put all the GLP-1 drug
trials together,
over an average of about a year,
they led to about 19 pounds
(8 kg) of weight loss.
And that folded in
some of the older GLP-1 drugs,
like liraglutide,
that don’t work as well.
If you just look at semaglutide,
the high-dose Ozempic
sold as Wegovy for weight loss,
we’re looking at more like
27 pounds (12 kg) lost,
which translates into about
three and a half inches (9 cm)
off the waist.
Which GLP-1 drug works best?
An oral version of Ozempic
has been developed.
Though it hasn’t been approved
for weight loss,
preliminary evidence suggests
it causes similar weight loss
to the injectable version.
The latest GLP-1 drug approved
for weight loss, tirzepatide,
sold as Zepbound,
appears to beat out semaglutide,
with nearly 19 percent
of body weight lost,
over 40 pounds (18 kg),
with more like five and a half
inches (14 cm) off the waist.
How does that compare
to bariatric surgery?
It’s actually not that far off
from long-term
surgical weight loss.
Now, remember,
these are averages.
Bariatric surgery
doesn’t always work.
The failure rate
for the gold standard procedure
is approximately 20 percent,
but not everyone responds
to the GLP-1 drugs either.
In the big Ozempic trials,
about a third of people were
"super responders,"
but as many as one in six didn’t
lose significant weight at all,
even after taking the drug
for more than a year.
So, despite impressive results
at a population level,
up to 20 percent of patients
fail to achieve
significant weight loss
with either surgical
or drug-based approaches.
Here’s the longest trial
to date,
four years of high-dose Ozempic
for weight loss at the end of Year Two.
The average weight loss was
about 10 percent;
so, some lost even more weight,
and sometimes,
a lot more weight,
some lost less,
and some even gained weight,
as much as maybe 40 pounds
(18 kg),
even after continuing
to inject the drug for years.
OK, but the most striking thing
about this graph is the plateau.
They were being injected with
the drug the whole four years,
but weight loss stalled
after only about a year.
This happened in study after
study after study after study,
with both Ozempic
and the newer tirzepatide.
So, even under
the best of circumstances,
with the most potent GLP-1 drugs
taken at the highest
allowable dose
for at least a year
to obtain the full weight loss,
we’re only looking at
a 34-pound (15 kg) drop
before the weight loss stops.
So, if you look at all three
of the original
placebo-controlled
Ozempic weight loss trials,
the participants
started out obese,
and after more than a year
on the drug
(when it effectively
stopped working),
they were still obese.
They were certainly less obese,
but still obese.
Then, to keep yourself
at that same level of obese,
you still have
to keep injecting it
at, like, $1,000 a month,
or you’ll go back to your
original level of obese.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you hear about any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
I also wrote a
mini book on Ozempic.
Available in softcover,
e-book, and audio versions.
Check it out on NutritionFacts.org.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.